<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Academic</title>
    <link>https://example.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 13:14:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hu2afe7b932772882c44ee7f7c5c4ca48a_10411_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ABC with Bayesian Neural networks</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/abc-neuralnet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 13:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/abc-neuralnet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Modern population genomics inference increasingly relies on complex stochastic models for which likelihood functions are either analytically intractable or computationally prohibitive to evaluate. This challenge is particularly acute in population genetics, evolutionary biology, and systems biology, where both coalescent and forward-time simulators can generate data under sophisticated models, but the corresponding likelihood functions remain intractable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) provides a likelihood-free framework for parameter inference in such settings. The fundamental principle of ABC relies on the intuition that simulated data sets with summary statistics close to those observed are likely to have been generated by similar parameter values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in deep learning offer promising solutions to preform likelihood-free parameter inference in a Bayesian framework. Neural networks can learn complex mappings between high-dimensional summary statistics and parameter spaces, effectively learning an implicit likelihood or posterior approximation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;thomasbrazier.github.io/abcneuralnet/&#34;&gt;abcneuralnet&lt;/a&gt; R package implements four state-of-the-art Bayesian deep learning approaches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concrete Dropout: Provides rigorous uncertainty quantification through approximate variational inference, specifically a refinement of dropout as variational Bayesian approximation where the dropout rate is learned during inference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monte Carlo Dropout: A simpler dropout approach, which offers uncertainty estimation through stochastic forward passes, yet requiring careful tuning of the dropout rate hyper-parameter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep Ensemble: A highly efficient ensemble approach delivering robust predictions through model averaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TabNet-ABC: Combines interpretable attention mechanisms with traditional ABC regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each method addresses different aspects of the ABC inference problem, with their own advantages and limitations, while maintaining compatibility with existing ABC workflows and providing rigorous uncertainty quantification essential for scientific inference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funded research projects</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/funded-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 13:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/funded-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of the different research projects I was involved in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anr.fr/Project-ANR-19-CE12-0019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANR Hotrec&lt;/a&gt;, coordinator: Laurent Duret (supervisor: Sylvain Glémin), coordinated by CNRS, UMR 6553 ECOBIO, University of Rennes, 2020-2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anr.fr/Project-ANR-22-CE02-0024&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANR Cistransevol&lt;/a&gt;, coordinator: Thomas Lenormand (supervisor: Sylvain Glémin), coordinated by CNRS, UMR 6553 ECOBIO, University of Rennes, 2022-2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3030/101115983&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ERC Starting Grant Evol-SV&lt;/a&gt;, coordinator: Claire Mérot (supervisor), coordinated by CNRS, UMR 6553 ECOBIO, University of Rennes, 2023-2028&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
